<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="webconsole">
<title>Web Console</title>

<section> 
	<title>Overview</title> 
	<para>
The Hedwig Web Console is a web based administration tool for working with Hedwig Mail server.
	</para>
	<para><graphic fileref="images/webconsole.png"/></para>
</section>

<section> 
	<title>Running the Web Console</title> 
	<para>
Download the hedwig-web-{version}.war file and install the war distribution.
Then you can point your web browser at the URL.
		<itemizedlist>
		    <listitem>
		        <para>http://localhost:8080/hedwig-web-{version}/</para>
		    </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
And hey presto, you should now have the Web Console running.
	</para>
</section>

<section> 
	<title>Configuring the Web Console</title> 
	<para>
Copy <emphasis>default.properties</emphasis> from Hedwig server's <emphasis>conf</emphasis> directory to <emphasis>WEB-INF</emphasis>.
Web Console is used by limited number of users, so change the <emphasis>jdbc.maxActive</emphasis> and <emphasis>jdbc.maxIdle</emphasis> value to smaller value.  
	</para>
	<para>
To enable access to the Web Console, you must create a new username/password combination and associate the role name <emphasis>manager</emphasis> with it.
Web Console defaults to a properties file stored at <emphasis>WEB-INF/users.properties</emphasis>, 
which can be edited with any text editor.
This file might look like this:
<screen>
admin=s3cret:manager
</screen> 
which defines the username and password used by this individual to log on, and the role names he or she is associated with.
	</para>
</section>

<section> 
	<title>Using the Web Console</title> 
	<section> 
		<title>Accounts</title> 
		<para>
You can create, update or delete accounts in this menu.
		</para>
		<para>
And you can import multiple accounts using <emphasis>Import</emphasis> menu.
Accounts are imported using a colon delimited text file.
The following fields are required for accounts import.
			<table>
				<title>Import file format</title>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Field</entry>
							<entry>Form</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Address</entry>
							<entry>The email address of the account.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Password</entry>
							<entry>The password of the account.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Maximum size</entry>
							<entry>The maximum disk space that the account may use.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Forwarding</entry>
							<entry>The email address you want to forward messages to.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
If fields are empty or omitted, default value is used for that field.  
Following is a sample import file.
<screen>
joe@domain.com:s3cret:1024:joe@gmail.com
bill@domain.com
jane@domain.com:tiger:
kara@domain.com:::nicole@nate.com
</screen>
		</para>
	</section>	
	<section>
		<title>Fetch Account</title>
		<para>
Hedwig can download messages from POP3 accounts on other servers.
Email downloads are delivered to the selected account.
You can fetch external account from <emphasis>Fetch</emphasis> menu in the <emphasis>Edit Account</emphasis> page. 
		</para>
		<para>
			<variablelist>
	    		<varlistentry>
	    			<term>Name</term>
	    			<listitem>
	    				<para>The name of the external account. The name is in free text and can be anything you like.</para>
	    			</listitem>
	    		</varlistentry>
	    		<varlistentry>
	    			<term>Protocol</term>
	    			<listitem>
	    				<para>Currently only POP3. Support for other protocols, such as IMAP, may be added in future.</para>
	    			</listitem>
	    		</varlistentry>
	    		<varlistentry>
	    			<term>Server address &amp; TCP Port</term>
	    			<listitem>
	    				<para>The hostname and TCP/IP port of the server should connect to when downloading messages.</para>
	    			</listitem>
	    		</varlistentry>
	    		<varlistentry>
	    			<term>User name &amp; Password</term>
	    			<listitem>
	    				<para>
The user name and password the server should use when login to the external server.
This should be the same information that you normally enter in your email client when login to that account.
	    				</para>
	    			</listitem>
	    		</varlistentry>
	    		<varlistentry>
	    			<term>SSL</term>
	    			<listitem>
						<para>
If the external server requires an encrypted connection(SSL), check the <emphasis>Use SSL</emphasis> option.
						</para>
	    			</listitem>
	    		</varlistentry>
	    		<varlistentry>
	    			<term>Settings</term>
	    			<listitem>
	    				<para>
If you select <emphasis>Delete messages immediately</emphasis>, server will delete the messages from the external server right after downloading them.
The opposite, <emphasis>Do not delete messages</emphasis>, causes server not to delete messages on the external server.
	    				</para>
	    			</listitem>
	    		</varlistentry>
	    	</variablelist>
		</para>
	</section>
	<section> 
		<title>Aliases</title> 
		<para>
You can create, update or delete aliases in this menu.
		</para>
		<para>
Aliases are used to forward email from one specific address to another.
Imagine them as addresses without a mailbox; instead of having their own mailbox, they store received messages in another account's mailbox.
This can be useful if you want to monitor several email addresses, but only have one real email account on the server.
For example, you may want to receive email messages sent to webmaster@domain.com, feedback@domain.com and yourname@domain.com, but you just want to create the webmaster@domain.com account instead of 3 different accounts.
Then feedback@domain.com and yourname@domain.com can be made aliases of webmaster@domain.com.			
		</para>
	</section>	
</section>	

</chapter>
